# VAIBHAV SINHA

#### SUMMARY

Senior Big Data Engineer with 5 years of experience in serving IT solutions to leading organizations in the world. I am proficient in building and managing data pipelines, finding meanings in data and proposing data & analytics solutions to businesses.

#### **EMPLOYMENT**

#### Accenture

Software Engineering Sr. Analyst (December, 2014 – Present)
Software Engineering Analyst (September, 2012 – December, 2014)
Software Engineering Associate (June, 2011 – September, 2012)

# MAJOR PROJECTS

### **Enterprise Data Lake (Client: leading European insurance provider)**

Scope: Data Migration from traditional RDBMS to HDFS and ensuring availability of data to business users.

- Extract data from various MySQL tables and importing on HDFS using Sqoop using parquet format and snappy compression base.
- Process the data from CSV.
- Perform data cleansing, create hive external tables and querying them on impala.
- Analytics on data using various impala queries on Hue.
- Writing python scripts to automate the data migration.
- Key technologies: Sqoop, Hive, Impala, Hue

# Marketing Campaign Efficiency – Sentiment Analysis (Client: leading US supermarket)

Scope: To monitor efficiency of various marketing campaigns among social media user bases at various time.

- Present visualized results to business to form product marketing strategy.
- Real-time streaming of data and saving into HDFS system.
- Data cleansing and formatting into hive tables.
- Visualizing the data using apache SOLR and presenting the results to business.
- Key technologies: Flume, Hive, Impala, SOLR, Hue

#### Log Analysis (client: leading European insurance provider)

Scope: To join data logs from 3 sources and find user access patterns

- Import logs to Hadoop and perform data cleansing and merging.
- Used Spark Unified stack to identify data patterns in the logs and present the data to business.
- Key Technologies: Sqoop, Flume, Hive, Spark, Spark-SQL

# **Proof of Concept for Big Data offerings (client: Internal)**

Scope: Building PoC Applications (Proof of Concept) for Big Data Analytics

- Identifying various tools and technologies available in market for analytics implementations
- Prepared user materials for trade-offs between various technologies and their maturity level.
- Created PoCs to implement queries about Big Data product in the market
- Key Technologies: MS office suite, infographics, Big Data stack, Journals (e.g. Gartner, HBR)

Intern

(Jan, 2011 - May, 2011)

# **Project – Guidance Tool**

Scope: Guidance Tool to monitor KPIs (Key Performance Indicators) at various management levels

- Built from scratch a tool which provides dashboards to track and manage KPIs of projects at various levels of management.
- Guidance Tool provided pertinent views to all the stake holders thus identifying areas which require interventions
  and track the progress of such actions.

# LANGUAGES AND TECHNOLOGIES

Big Data: Hadoop, Sqoop, Flume, Hive, Impala, Spark, SOLR, Pig

Databases (SQL & NoSQL): Cassandra, MongoDB, IBM DB2, MySQL

Operating System: Linux, Windows, z/OS

Languages: Core Java, Python. Also know: Scala, R

Tools & IDEs: Eclipse, PyCharm, Hue, Also Know: Adobe Marketing Cloud.

# **EDUCATION**

Dhirubhai Ambani Institute of Information and Communication Technology, Gandhinagar. *Masters of Science (Information and Communication Technology)* – 9.2/10.0 CGPA

Birla Institute of Technology, Mesra.

Bachelors of Computer Applications – 8.5/10.0 CGPA

# **CERTIFICATIONS AND COURSES**

- Certified Application Developer Massachusetts Institute of Tech., USA in collaboration with Accenture
- M101P MongoDB Developer *MongoDB University* (Scored in top 10% globally)
- Certified Database Associate IBM
- Microsoft Certified Programmer *Microsoft Corp.*
- Certified Insurance Generalist Accenture
- Certified Scrum Trained Professional Accenture

# ADDITIONAL EXPERIENCE AND AWARDS

- AASEGP Accenture initiative where I mentor, coach and connect with 1000+ new joiners and college grads every year. (awarded Top mentor in Accenture India)
- Winner of Accenture's highest award 'Accenture Celebrates Excellence', for Innovation
- Certificate of Commendation from Global CTO of a major client for Innovation and Excellence.
- Winner of Accenture Greenfield Topper Award
- Member of Annual Fest Team in college raised sponsorships and organized event with INR 1 Million budget
- Authoring articles and white papers on technology trends and disruptions.
- Created and delivered trainings to improve technology and business skills.